<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
	Copyright (c) 2005, 2006 Springsite BV (The Netherlands) and others
	All rights reserved. This program and the accompanying materials
	are made available under the terms of the Eclipse Public License v1.0
	which accompanies this distribution, and is available at
	http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html
-->

<!--
	@author <a href="mtaal@elver.org">Martin Taal</a>
	@version $Revision: 1.7 $ $Date: 2006/09/14 04:36:37 $
-->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
	"-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
	"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document> 
	<header> 
		<title>Changelog</title> 
	</header> 
	<body>
		<p>Gives an overview of changes in different releases over time</p>
		<p></p>
		<p>
		<strong>From 12 September 2006: for changelog and release notes see the emft website: <a href="http://www.eclipse.org/emft/news/release-notes.php">here</a></strong>
		</p>
		<!--
		<p></p>
		<p>
		<strong>Release: 0.7.5 ALPHA - 27 Augustus 2006</strong>
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Changed default column names for version and synthetic id to e_version and e_id. These names should be valid for most databases and prevent nameclashes.
			You can be backward compatible by setting the names back to the old values using the relevant options, (see <a href="options.html">here</a>).</li>
			<li>For EAttribute, Unique attribute is not used anymore to set unique on property/column level.</li>
			Toplevel nested annotations not used anymore JoinColumns, etc.
		</ul>
		-->
		<p></p>
		<p>
		<strong>Release: 0.7.2 ALPHA - 7 June 2006</strong>
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li><strong>Changed source of annotations</strong>: ejb3 annotation now use ejb.elver.org, Elver specific annotation now use
			annotation.elver.org, Hibernate specific annotations now use hibernate.elver.org. 
			For backward compatibility all ejb annotations can also still be used together with 
			annotation.elver.org.</li>
			<li><strong>The hibernate jar files have been moved to a separate plugin: org.eclipse.emf.teneo.hibernate.libraries</strong>. This plugin contains the 
			Hibernate 3.2 version. If you want to use a different Hibernate version then please replace the hibernate jars in this plugin (in the 
			installation directory of Eclipse). In a later release this will possibly be made easier.</li>
			<li><strong>All table and column names are now in lowercase.</strong> The casing can be controlled with an option
			(see <a href="options.html">here</a>).</li>
			<li>EJB/Persistence annotations can be set on the EDataType, see <a href="ejb3_features.html#edatatype">here</a>.</li>
			<li>Cleaned up the interface for setting properties. The HbDataStore.setHibernateProperties can 
			be used to set Hibernate specific properties, the HbDataStore.setPersistenceProperties can be used to set Elver specific 
			persistence properties.</li>
			<li>The interface for getting the session has been changed, instead of getSession you need to call getSessionFactory().openSession() on the 
			HbDataStore.</li>
			<li>Added different runtime properties (see <a href="options.html">here</a>), for example to handle column/table names which are too long.</li>
			<li>Multi level mapped super classes in the inheritance tree were not supported, this has been fixed now.</li>
			<li>Solved a bug related to mapping of non-indexed (bag) relations, this issue occurs when a type has a reference to itself.</li>
			<li>Solved a bug in handling of enumerates (String enumerates were stored as int)</li>
			<li>Unique attribute on eattributes is now used to generate a unique constraint</li>
			<li>Solved a bug related to handling of non-unique, non-indexed, one-to-many relations</li>
			<li>Added modest support for multiple inheritance (see <a href="inheritance.html#Multiple+Inheritance+Support">here</a>)</li>
			<li>Added/changed support for the following annotations:
				<ul>
				<li>Added secondary table(s), embedded id and lob, (see <a href="ejb3_features.html">here</a>)</li>
			<li>Added idbag</li>
			<li>Added type annotation on EDataType to support UserType</li>
			<li>Added columns (multiple) annotation</li>
			<li>Added transient annotation on EClass level (see <a href="ejb3_features.html#transient">here</a>).</li>
			<li>Changed the format of the Elver specific Indexed and Unique annotation (see <a href="hibernate_relations.html">here</a>)</li>
			</ul></li>
			<li>Testcases are now also run using MS Sql Server 2000/2005.</li>
			<li><strong>Default cacheprovider has been set to org.hibernate.cache.HashtableCacheProvider</strong>, because of ehcache issues which occur when using
			ehcache with the default values (and hibernate 3.2), see <a href="hibernate_details.html#Default+cacheprovider+has+been+set+to+org.hibernate.cache.HashtableCacheProvider">here</a>. You can override this default setting by setting the hibernate.cache.provider_class property with the cache provider class you want to use.
			</li>
		</ul>
		<p></p>
		<p>
		<strong>Release: 0.7.1 ALPHA - 8 May 2006</strong>
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li>EList (or multiplicity unbounded) is supported for Dynamic EMF persistency.</li>
			<li>Added support for Qualifying EClass names (based on an option) (see <a href="options.html">here</a>).</li> 
			<li>Added Eclipse menu option to generate hibernate mapping file, the mapping file can be used instead of automatic mapping (see <a href="hibernate_details.html#orgeneration">here</a>).</li>
			<li>Solved a mapping bug which occurs when an id and column annotation are combined, thanks to Douglas Bitting for analysing and reporting this issue.</li>
			<li>Added support for PrimaryKeyJoinColumn for Hibernate, PrimaryKeyJoinColumn is translated to a one-to-one with constrained="true".</li>
			<li>Added automatic escaping of table names and column names of primitive types, join table names are not automatically escaped. This should be done manually 
			by adding a JoinTable annotation (see <a href="hibernate_details.html#escaping">here</a>).</li>
			<li>JoinColumns were not supported correctly, has been fixed, thanks to Douglas Bitting for providing the patch.</li>
			<li>Added option to control the name of the automatically created version and id columns (see <a href="options.html">here</a>).</li>
			<li>Added support for xsd:list</li>
		</ul>
		<p></p>
		<p>
		<strong>Release: 0.7.0 ALPHA - 21 April 2006</strong>
		</p>
		<p>This release is a major rewrite compared to the previous release. This release is not backward compatible, 
		mapping logic as well as interfaces have changed. An overview of the changes/new features:</p>
		<ul>
			<li>OR Mapping is now done on the basis of the ecore model (EPackages), source code is not parsed anymore, 
			see <a href="overview.html">the overview</a>.</li>
			<li>Automatic runtime creation of mapping, no intermediate hibernate.hbm.xml required anymore.</li>
			<li>Support for ejb3 like annotations such as mapped superclass, composite id, UniqueConstraint etc. see 
			<a href="ejb3_features.html">here</a>.</li>
			<li>Support for dynamic emf (with limitations though), see <a href="dynamic.html">here</a>.</li>
			<li>No extra ESet columns: before for each primitive type efeature an additional ESet column was created. 
			From this release this is not done anymore.</li>
			<li>Added support for different class loader strategies, see <a href="hibernate_details.html">here</a>.</li>
			<li>Solved issues related to nullability of enum fields and using enums in primary keys.</li>
			<li>Added option to control if the database schema is updated at startup, see <a href="options.html">here</a>.</li>
			<li>Added new sections to the website: an overview, related to ejb3, options, dynamic EMF, etc.</li>
			<li>Upgraded to EMF 2.2 and Hibernate 3.1.3.</li>
			<li>Added eager loading of containment relations, is controlled by annotation, default 
			behavior is lazy and not eager</li>
			<li>Tracking modification on a resource does now work with lazy loading. Before setting
			tracking modification to true (or add an adapter) ment that the whole resource was loaded,
			this is now not required anymore.</li>
			<li>Cut and paste in a the editor is now supported by setting the Cascade annotation, see
			<a href="hibernate_details.html#cutpaste">here</a>.</li>
			<li>Main things which have been changed since the 0.3.* release:
			<ul>
			<li>HQL queries should now use EClass names and EFeature names instead of java class names/members. See the tutorials 
			on this website.</li>
			<li>Cleaned up the HibernateHelper interface, renamed HibernateHelper to HbHelper, introduced concept of a HbDataStore,
			see <a href="hbdatastore.html">here</a>.</li>
			<li>Replaced the Configuration Factory with a different more flexible approach, see <a href="hbdatastore.html">here</a>.</li>
			<li>FeatureMap support without generating additional source files, see <a href="featuremap.html">here</a>.</li>
			<li>The options which can be passed to the mapper and Elver runtime have been restructured, see 
			<a href="hbdatastore.html#options">here</a>.</li>
			<li>The previous annotations for inheritance mapping, indexed or unique have changed. see 
			<a href="inheritance.html">here</a> and <a href="hibernate_relations.html">here</a>.</li>
			<li>Added option to set all containment lists to eager loading, see <a href="hbdatastore.html#options">here</a>.</li>
			</ul></li>
		</ul>
		<p></p>
		<p>
		<strong>Release: 0.3.2 ALPHA - 15 November 2005</strong>
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li>New webpage which describes different topics related to mapping of 
		associations/relations, see <a href="hibernate_relations.html">here</a>.</li>
			<li>Added support for non-indexed relations in the database. EMF only supports
		indexed relations, however indexing of a relation is often not required and gives a performance
		penalty. It is now possible to specify with annotations that specific relations should
		not be indexed, see <a href="hibernate_relations.html#Mapping+non-indexed+relations">here</a>.</li>
			<li>The non-indexed annotations can be used for nm relations also, this allows 
			non-indexed nm relations to be persisted using one join table. See 
			<a href="hibernate_relations.html#Mapping+non-indexed+nm+relations">here</a>.
			</li>
			<li>Annotations can be used to force a join table also for 1:n relations, see 
			<a href="hibernate_relations.html#Support+duplicates%2C+Force+a+join+table+for+1%3An+relations">here</a>.
			</li>
			<li>Embedded types are now supported by tagging the embedded types with an annotation, 
			see <a href="hibernate_relations.html#Embedded+components">here</a>.</li>
			<li>It can now be specified, using an annotation, that a member is an 
		identifier for which Hibernate (or the database) must generate unique values, 
			see <a href="hibernate_details.html#Identifier+fields">here</a>.</li>
			<li>Upgraded to qdox 1.6, now also jdk1.5 constructions are supported when 
			generating hibernate mapping file.</li>
			<li>Solved an issue related to null-pointer exceptions when abstract types 
refered to eachother.</li>
			<li>Solved an issue which is related to types with interface="true" this issue
resulted in missing model fields in the mapping file.</li>
		</ul>
		<p></p>
		<p>
		<strong>Release: 0.3.1 ALPHA - 24 October 2005</strong>
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Now both table-per-classhierarchy and table-per-subclass 
				inheritance mapping is supported. These two
			inheritance mapping strategies are present in the elver submenu in the Eclipse plugin. 
				See <a href="inheritance.html">here</a> for more information.</li>
			<li>It is now possible to control the inheritance mapping separately for each class hierarchy
			by adding specific annotations in the model, see <a href="inheritance.html">here</a> for more 
			information.</li>
			<li>The mapping logic has been changed, now only implementation classes are present
			in the mapping file, interfaces are supported through Hibernate implicit polymorphism. 
			See <a href="hibernate_details.html#Why+Elver+explicitly+maps+implementation+classes+and+implicitly+maps+interfaces">here</a>
				 for more information on why this approach is chosen.</li>
			<li>XML Schema substitution group support has been added.</li>
			<li>It is now possible to register a HibernateConfigurationFactory, this allows the 
			customization of the creation of SessionFactories and other Hibernate configuration settings. 
			See <a href="hibernate_details.html#Configuration+Factory+or+add+your+own+Hibernate+Even+Listeners+%28and+other+customizations%29">here</a> for more information.</li>
			<li>A new createRegisterSessionFactory method has been made available. This method just 
			expects a property bag, this allows more flexible configuration of the SessionFactory
			(for example to specify a datasource instead of connection information).</li>
			<li>The container field in the database has been changed from a binary field
			to a varchar field. See <a href="hibernate_details.html#Storing+container+relation">here</a> for more
			information.</li>
			<li>Upgraded to the latest Hibernate release: 3.1rc2.</li>
			<li>Notifications are now dispatched when an elist/featuremap is loaded (see 
				<a href="hibernate_details.html#EList%2FFeaturemap+load+notification">here</a>), Hibernate now uses
				the property setters (with notifications) to set retrieved values from the 
				db in the EMF object, a future release will
			add an option to disable notifications during load time.</li>
			<li>Resource TrackingModification is not automatically enabled anymore at load time, the client should
			do this explicitly. The reason for this is that tracking modification is an expensive operation
			because it walks the complete containment tree.</li>
			<li>The OR Mapping file generator will now also specify the tablename. The tablename
			is based on the classname of the persisted entity.</li>
			<li>Solved the following issues:
			<ul>
			<li>In some cases a session was not disconnected with ELists
			in combination with HibernateResource.</li>
			<li>In case of a deeper inheritance structure the econtainer
			fields/columns were not correctly defined in tables. This resulted in
			low-level sql errors (incorrect type for getInt().... or something similar).</li>
			<li>The toString method of an EList loaded the elist, in Hibernate
			this resulted in concurrent modification errors in logging code. The decision is
			made that toString is not 'important' enough to load a elist.</li>
			</ul></li>
			<li>Source code is distributed together with the jar files.</li>
		</ul>
		<p></p>
		<p>
		<strong>Release: 0.3.0 ALPHA - 10 October 2005</strong>
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Solved issue: for many-to-many combined with subclassing: an incorrect 
			not-null attribute was placed in the many-to-many tag.</li>
			<li>Added support for a number of additional XML Schema constructions: 
				<a href="featuremap.html#FeatureMap+for+Mixed+content">mixed</a>,
			restriction, extension, etc. Many XML Schema constructions are now supported,
			see <a href="features_details.html">here</a>.</li>
			<li>Added getCrossReferencer function. This allows you to retrieve (from the 
				database) all objects which refer to a specific eobject. This function can 
				for example be
				used to check (and report) all delete constraints before an 
				object is deleted, see <a href="hibernate_helper.html">here</a>.</li>
			<li>Upgraded to Hibernate3.1rc1, for this release it is required to upgrade
				to the Hibernate3.1rc1 release, the Hibernate libraries are all present in
				the org.eclipse.emf.teneo.hibernate.runtime plugin. Note that in rc1 the 
				methods session.reconnect/disconnect have been deprecated.</li>
			<li>Restructured the Tutorial &amp; Information part of the website.</li>
		</ul>
		<p></p>
		<p>
		<strong>Release: 0.2.2 ALPHA - 30 September 2005</strong>
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Support for many-to-many (mn) relations has been added, is still very alpha
			but can be tried (see <a href="hibernate_details.html#Mapping+many-to-many+%28nm%29+relations">here</a> for more information).</li>
			<li>Solved a bug related to showing incorrect top level objects in a resource. 
		This was visible in the EMF editor because contained objects were displayed in the
		top of the editor. Credits to Pawel Sabina for identifying this issue and helping
		to solve it.</li>
			<li>It is now possible
		to select multiple packages when generating the hibernate.hbm.xml. Only one
		hibernate.hbm.xml file will be generated with all the mappings, this file is placed
		in the first selected package. Selecting multiple packages is only required
		if there are relations between classes of these packages. Note that this feature has not been tested
		thoroughly.</li>
			<li>Customize the load behavior of HibernateResource (see <a href="hibernateresources.html">here</a>):
		<ul> 
		<li>The implementation of the 
		HibernateResource has been changed so that the load behavior can easily be overridden by subclassing.</li>
		<li>The load behavior of the HibernateResource can also be controlled by 
			passing queries in the url or in the ehb file.</li>			
		</ul>
		</li>
			<li>Added possibility of XMI import and export to the resource utility. XMI 
		is more powerful than the XML export/import because XMI 
		supports multiple root objects when exporting/importing.
		 See <a href="resource_utility.html">here</a>.</li>
		</ul>
		<p></p>
		<p>
		<strong>Release: 0.2.1 ALPHA - 28 September 2005</strong>
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li>FeatureMap support has been added, see <a href="featuremap.html">here</a>
			 for more information.</li>
			<li>Container relation is now also stored in the child in the relation. This
		means that the eContainer and eContainerFeatureID is set in the EObject also when
		the EObject is read directly from the database.
			</li>
			<li>The resource utility has been improved. Now it is possible to validate the contents 
		by explicitly selecting the validate option.</li>
			<li>The plugin structure has been improved, more functions have been moved to 
			a generic plugin (org.eclipse.emf.teneo).</li>
		</ul>
		<p></p>
		<p>
		<strong>Release: 0.2.0.1 ALPHA - 19 September 2005</strong>
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Solved a very visible bug which resulted in an error in the editor. This error had the 
				following symptoms, only part of the data is persisted and the following 
				message is displayed in the console: <em>not-null property references a null or transient value</em>.
			</li>
			<li>Updated the website on various locations</li>
			<li>Solved an issue which resulted in class not found exceptions in the 
			runtime enhancement by cglib when starting eclipse with an open EMF editor</li>
		</ul>
		<p>To make use of the above changes the hibernate.hbm.xml has to be regenerated.</p>
		<p></p>
		<p><strong>First Release: 0.2.0 ALPHA was on 15 September 2005</strong></p>
	</body>
</document>
