<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
	Copyright (c) 2005, 2006 Springsite BV (The Netherlands) and others
	All rights reserved. This program and the accompanying materials
	are made available under the terms of the Eclipse Public License v1.0
	which accompanies this distribution, and is available at
	http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>Hibernate EMF Resources</title> 
    <notice>Describes the use of an EMF resource implemenation for Hibernate</notice>
    <abstract>The EMF Hibernate integration also contains a Resource implementation for
		integration with the EMF Editing Domain. The resource implementation
		extends the org.eclipse.emf.ecore.xmi.impl.XMIResourceImpl to enable easy importing 
		and exporting of XML to/from the relational store.
    </abstract> 
  </header> 
  <body>
	 <p></p>
    <section>
      <title>Resource URI</title>
      <p>The Hibernate EMFResource is registered using different extensions/protocols:</p>
	  <ul>
	  <li>Protocol: the Hibernate EMF Resource (factory) will be registered for the protocols hibernate and ehb</li>
	  <li>Extension: the Hibernate EMF Resource (factory) will be registered for the extensions hibernate and ehb</li>
	  </ul>
	  <p>When the hibernate protocol is used to retrieve a Resource then the resource 
		  needs to know how to reach a data store.  This is done by passing the registration name
	  of a HbDataStore to the resource with the org.eclipse.emf.teneo.Resource.DS_NAME_PARAM parameter. 
	  </p>
	  <p>An example of a URI which returns a Hibernate resource: <em>hibernate://dsname=library</em>.</p>
	</section>
    <section>
      <title>Hibernate Resource and session/transaction specifics</title>
      <p>The Hibernate Resource opens a session when it is loaded for the first time.
		 A transaction is started when the load starts and committed at the end of the load.
		  This session is disconnected at the end of the load action.</p>
		<p>The save action will reconnect the session, begin a transaction, do an update of
		  the datastore and then commit and disconnect.</p>
		 <p>In one of the next releases a new resource implementation will be added which will create a new session
		 for each load and save action.</p>
	</section>
    <section>
      <title>Validation</title>
      <p>The Hibernate Resource automatically validates its content (the EObjects) when the
		  resource is saved. This validation makes use of the EMF validation framework throug calls to
		  the Diagnostician.INSTANCE.validate method. Validation fails when a ERROR level Diagnostic is
		  encountered. In this case the resource save method will throw a org.eclipse.emf.teneo.StoreValidationException. 
		  This exception has a method to retrieve all Diagnostics.</p>
	</section>
		<section>
	  		<title>Standard load behavior: Top level types</title>
      <p>When a Hibernate EMF resource is loaded then only the so called top-level types are directly present in 
		  the resource contents. Top-level types are types which are not used as the 
		  the child in a containment relation. The assumption is that all contained types can be reached
	  from a top-level type.</p>
	  <p>See also the <a href="knownissues.html">Known Issues</a>.</p>
	  </section>
	 <section><title>Customizing load behavior</title>
	 <p>It is possible to customize what the resource actually loads from the database.</p>
		 <section><title>Extend the resource implementation in java</title>
			<p>It is possible to customize the load behavior by overriding the loadFromStore method
				in the HibernateResource. This method gets a PersistenceManager and should return a list of 
				objects read from the Hibernate datastore.
			</p>
		 </section>
		 <section><title>Set specific queries to load the resource</title>
			<p>There are two ways to pass specific queries to the HibernateResource. The first method
				is using uri parameters:</p>
			 <p><em>hibernate://?dsname=mystore&amp;query1=FROM Writer</em></p>
			 <p>You can pass multiple queries by using parameter names which start with query, for
			 example query1, query2 etc.</p>
			 <p>The other way to pass queries to the resource are to specify them in the 
			 .ehb file (see resource utility <a href="resource_utility.html">here</a>). An
			 example (commented out) of this can be found in the ehb file <a href="samples/library.ehb">here</a>.</p>
		 </section>
	 </section>
    <section>
      <title>Sharing one Session between Resources, One transaction when saving multiple resources</title>
		<p>As a standard behavior the resource will create its own session at load time.
		However, there are cases when you want to use one session to load and save multiple resources. This 
		is for example the case when there are references between objects in different resources. 
		In this case the load and save actions of multiple resources should use the same session and be done
		in the same transaction.</p>
		<p>To support this Teneo has the concept of a SessionController. A SessionController manages one session
		for multiple resources. A SessionController is registered using a specific name. When a resource is opened this
		name is passed as an uri parameter. Using this name the HibernateResource can then find the SessionController
		and retrieve a session. When a HibernateResource has a SessionController then the HibernateResource does not itself 
		create a session or begin and commit transactions. Beginning and committing transactions is the responsibility
		of the application itself.</p>
		<p>Here is some example code illustrating the use of a SessionController:</p>
		<source>
	SessionController sc = new SessionController();

	// when creating a SessionController you have to pass your HbDataStore instance
	sc.setHbDataStore(hbDataStore);

	// register the SessionController, the name is used in the uri of the resource
	SessionController.registerSessionController("testsc", sc);

	// create an uri using the SessionController name
	URI uri1 = URI.createURI("hibernate://?" + HibernateResource.SESSION_CONTROLLER_PARAM + "=testsc&amp;query1=from Book");
	URI uri2 = URI.createURI("hibernate://?" + HibernateResource.SESSION_CONTROLLER_PARAM + "=testsc&amp;query1=from Writer");
	// resourceSet has to be set before somehow..
	final Resource res1 = resourceSet.createResource(uri1);
	final Resource res2 = resourceSet.createResource(uri2);
	
	// now load the resources 
	sc.getSession().beginTransaction();
	res1.load(Collections.EMPTY_MAP);
	res2.load(Collections.EMPTY_MAP);
	sc.getSession().getTransaction().commit();
	
	// do something usefull with your loaded resources...

	// and save them
	sc.getSession().beginTransaction();
	res1.save(Collections.EMPTY_MAP);
	res2.save(Collections.EMPTY_MAP);
	sc.getSession().getTransaction().commit();
		</source>
		<p><strong>Loading different EObjects (refering to eachother) in different resources can have side-effects if
		there are containment relations to and from these EObjects (with resolving=false). 
		If the containment relation is non-resolving then
		EMF will place an EObject always in the same resource as its container. If you use queries to load your resources
		then the containers are loaded also. For example: assume EObjects A1 and A2 both have container A0. If one resource
		loads A1 then A0 is also loaded automatically and A0 and A1 are in the same resource. If then a second resource loads
		A2 then A2 will be placed in the first resource because its container is located there. Overall this results in 
		unpredictable behavior. So: to correctly work with multiple resources the containment relations should be set to
		resolving = true.</strong></p>
		</section>
		<section>
	  		<title>Closing a resource</title>
      <p>The Hibernate EMF resource can be closed by calling the unload method. 
		  This method will close the disconnected session. In case a SessionController is used
		  the unload method will just nullify the internal session member, you should close
		  the session explicitly.</p>
	</section>
    <section>
      <title>Other aspects</title>
		<section><title>Resource use after Hibernate exception</title>
		<p>When a Hibernate error/exception occurs when working with a Hibernate resource it can not
		be used anymore and should be unloaded (closed).</p>
		<p>In a future resource implementation this issue will be solved.</p>
		</section>
		<section>
	  		<title>Closing a resource</title>
      <p>The Hibernate EMF resource can be closed by calling the unload method. 
		  This method will close the disconnected session.</p>
	  </section>
	</section>
  </body> 
</document>
