<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
	Copyright (c) 2005, 2006 Springsite BV (The Netherlands) and others
	All rights reserved. This program and the accompanying materials
	are made available under the terms of the Eclipse Public License v1.0
	which accompanies this distribution, and is available at
	http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html
-->

<!--
	@author <a href="mtaal@elver.org">Martin Taal</a>
	@version $Revision: 1.2 $ $Date: 2006/09/13 10:42:34 $
-->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
	"-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
	"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document> 
	<header> 
		<title>Known issues (updated 13 September 2006)</title> 
	</header> 
	<body>
		<p><br/></p>
		<p>
		<strong>From 13 September 2006: for open issues please visit the EMFT <a href="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?product=EMFT&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;query_format=advanced&amp;order=map_components.name">open bugs</a>
		page.</strong></p>
		<p><br/></p>
		<p>This page describes known issues (and possible work arounds) and gives an estimate on when they will be solved.</p>
		<p>Open issue(s):</p>
		<ul>
		<li><strong>Objects are not loaded in the resource, or the resource is empty:</strong> The standard behavior of a Hibernate resource is to only read types which have no container in the model. All other EObjects can 
		be reached from these top-entities. However, this means that even if an EObject instance does not have a container but <em>can be</em> contained according to the model then
		it will still not be loaded in the resource. A common model is a an object which contains itself, for example a folder-like
		model. <strong>Workaround</strong>: to workaround this issue you should load the resource using specific queries, see customizing load behavior <a href="hibernateresources.html">here</a>.</li>
		</ul>
		<p>The following issues have been solved in the 0.7.0 release:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Enumerated types are not supported as primarykey/id fields. This will be solved in the next release. 
		<strong>Is solved with the remark that the EnumeratedType should be Seriliazable.</strong></li>
		<li>Enumerated type fields can not be nullable, they must be set as required. This will be solved in the next release.</li>
		<li>Java Annotations to Ecore, mapping file error: When starting the runtime the following error
	message is displayed (using the Library example):<em>Association references unmapped class: Book</em>.
 The issue is related to the fact that the model is generated from annotated java. Currently Elver uses the annotations in the source code to resolve java types. The java sources generated from the uml/xml schema have fully quallified names in the type attribute of the model tag:
	<source>
     * @model type="org.eclipse.example.library.Writer"
     * @generated
     */
    EList getWriters();
	</source>
<p>
While in the case the java annotations are the input the emf tutorial tells you to do this:</p>
<source>
  /**
   * @model type="Writer" containment="true"
   */
  List getWriters();
</source>
<p>Elver should automatically resolve the Writer to a org.eclipse.example.library.Writer interface but does not do this. 
As a workaround you should specify the fully qualified class name in the type annotation.</p>
	</li>
		</ul>
		<p></p>

		<p>The following issues have been solved in the 3.2 release:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>After an elist/featuremap is loaded a notification is sent out. 
		See <a href="hibernate_details.html#EList%2FFeaturemap+load+notification">here</a> for more information.
		Apparently this notification results in exceptions and double entries in rich client tree viewers.
		See the posts on the mailing list for this: <a href="http://comments.gmane.org/gmane.comp.java.emf.persistency/139">post 1</a>, 
		<a href="http://comments.gmane.org/gmane.comp.java.emf.persistency/144">post 2</a>. As a workaround you should 'catch' the notification
		in the notifychanged of the EObjects ItemProvider. This will be solved in the next release
		or the function will be disabled until it is more stable.
		<strong>Load notification on EList load has been disabled.</strong></li>
		</ul>
		<p>The following issues have been solved in the 3.1 release:</p>
		<ul>
			<li>On the mailinglist (see <a href="http://comments.gmane.org/gmane.comp.java.emf.persistency/95">here</a>) 
				it was reported that when saving a HibernateResource the 
			error 'session already closed' occurs. This issue is not present (anymore) in the
			current development version so is solved with the next release on 
				24 Oct.</li>
			<li>In some cases a session will not be disconnected with ELists
			in combination with HibernateResource. This results in errors in the
			resource unload action and open transactions (is solved in 3.1).</li>
			<li>In case of a deeper inheritance structure the econtainer
			fields/columns are not correctly set in the relational tables. This results in
			low-level sql errors, incorrect type for getInt().... or something similar
			 (is solved in 3.1).</li>
			<li>The toString method of an EList loads the elist, in Hibernate
			this results in concurrent modification errors in logging code. The decision is
			made that toString is not 'important' enough to load a elist 
			(is solved in 3.1).</li>
			<li>multiple inheritance of an EObject from two EMF interfaces does
				not work correctly. An example is the GlobalAddress in the ExtendedPO example.
				The GlobalAddress inherits from both the Address and the GlobalLocation interfaces.
				Hibernate does not allow the definition of multiple 'parent' interfaces. 
				<em>From the 3.1 release the mapping logic has changed so that only implementation
				classes are present in the mapping file. This effectively solves this issue.</em>
				 </li>
		</ul>
		<p>
			Previous issues have been solved or a workaround or description is
			displayed on the <a href="troubleshooting.html">troubleshooting</a> page.
		</p>
	</body>
</document>
