<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
	Copyright 2005-2006, Elver.org (http://www.elver.org).

	Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
	you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
	You may obtain a copy of the License at

		http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
	distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
	WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
	See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
	limitations under the License.
-->

<!--
	@author <a href="mtaal@elver.org">Martin Taal</a>
	@version $Revision: 1.1 $ $Date: 2006/08/03 09:58:07 $
-->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
	"-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
	"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document> 
	<header> 
		<title>Subversion</title> 
	</header> 
	<body>
		<p>The source code of the EMF - Hibernate integration is stored in a <a href="http://subversion.tigris.org/">Subversion</a> repository.
			The subversion url is: svn://svn.elver.org/elver with anonymous login.</p>
		<p></p>
		<p>
			<strong>The source code in subversion is updated on a daily basis and contains experimental
				new features which can (temporarily) break already existing functionality and tests.
				There is no guarantee that the code in subversion will work in anyway.</strong></p>
		<section id="projects">
			<title>Projects in Subversion</title>
		<p>
			The relevant Hibernate related projects within the repository are:
		</p>
			<ul>
			<li>org.elver.store: this project contains general code used by the JPOX as well as the Hibernate runtime layer.</li>
			<li>org.elver.store.eclipse: this project contains general code for the eclipse menu options used by the JPOX as well as the Hibernate runtime layer.</li>
			<li>org.elver.store.annotations: this project contains code for reading and generating annotations.</li>
			<li>org.elver.store.hibernate: this project contains the EMF - Hibernate mapping and runtime layer.</li>
			<li>org.elver.store.hibernate.eclipse: this project contains the resource utility Eclipse plugins.</li>
			<li>org.elver.store.samples: this project contains the examples and model information used in the testcases.</li>
			<li>org.elver.store.commontest: this project contains the test case part which is common for Hibernate and JPOX</li>
			<li>org.elver.store.hibernate.test: the hibernate specific part of the tests</li>
			<li>org.elver.store.tutorial: the tutorials used on this website</li>
			</ul>
		<p>
			Other projects in subversion are related to an integration between EMF and JSF and Hibernate.
		</p>
		<p>The projects have dependencies which are managed by the plugin dependencies in
		the Manifest.MF</p>
		<p>Sometimes projects will have a dependency to a org.hibernate plugin project (not present in svn). 
			This is used 
		to debug hibernate. When checking out the development projects these dependencies can
			be replaced by the corresponding hibernate jar file.</p>
		<p>
			Within each project there is a sub folder called trunk which contains the 
			latest version. Other versions are present in the branch/version subfolders.
		</p>
		<p>We use the standard Eclipse code format with the line length set to 120, the formatter profile
		can be downloaded <a href="../download/elver-code-profile.xml">here</a>.</p>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
