<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
	Copyright 2005-2006, Elver.org (http://www.elver.org).
 
 	Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
 	you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
 	You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
 		http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
 	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 	distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 	WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 	See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 	limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>Upgrading EMF - Hibernate Plugins</title> 
    <abstract>Describes specific aspects of upgrading the EMF - Hibernate plugins
    </abstract> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
	  <section>
	  	<title>Changes from a 0.3.* to the 0.7.0 release</title>
	  	<p>Going from the 0.3.* release to the 0.7.0 release Elver has changed in many places. The main change is that it is not 
	  	required anymore to generate an intermediate hibernate.hbm.xml file. The mapping is done at runtime based on the ecore file.</p>
		<p>The main entrance class the HibernateHelper has been replaced by HbHelper. The interface of this class is cleaner than its
		predecessor. A new class has been introduced: HbDataStore. This class represents the combination of a set of EPackages and a
		relational store. The HbDataStore can be used for different purposes. See <a href="hbdatastore.html">here</a>.
		</p>
		<p>Another major change is that in the HQL queries the EClass name should now be used instead of the java class names.</p>
	  </section>
	  <section>
	  	<title>Regenerate hibernate.hbm.xml after upgrading</title>
	  	<p>New functionality and bug fixes can result in changes in the generated hibernate.hbm.xml.
	  New versions can depend on an updated hibernate.hbm.xml. So after upgrading it is sometimes 
	  necessary to regenerate the hibernate.hbm.xml file.</p>
	  </section>
	  <section>
      <title>Upgrade through the Update Manager: Search for upgrades... or Search for new Features...</title>
     	<p>Depending on how you defined valid upgrades in 
			 <em>windows &gt; preferences &gt; Install/Updates</em>, it is possible that
			 the 'Search for Upgrades of installed features' in the update manager will
			 not find the updated EMF-Hibernate plugin. If this happens then the 'Search for new Features..' option
			 should be chosen in the Update Manager.
		</p>
		<p>After the Elver plugins has been downloaded the 
			 update manager will detect that the 'new' feature is in fact an upgrade of an already
			 installed feature. The old-version of the feature will automatically be disabled.
			 This is visible in the Manage Configuration function in the <em>Help &gt; Sofware Updates</em> 
			 menu.
		</p>
	 </section>
    <section>
     	<title>Changed datamodel after upgrading</title>
		<p>The OR Mapper is also updated to solve issues and add functionality. This can mean that the 
			hibernate.hbm.xml generated by the OR Mapper differs from one version to another. Resulting in a
			different database schema. When the database already exists from previous versions this can mean
			that the new expected database schema does not correspond with the old database schema.
		</p>
		<p>Hibernate will try to correct differences by adding tables and columns. However not all changes
			can be automatically repaired.</p>
		<p>The issues can be resolved by manually adding missing columns. Another way to resolve the above issue 
			is to start again with a new empty database.
			Hibernate will then automatically create new tables which adhere to the package.jdo</p>
		<p>For the longer term we are considering to offer tools which will better facilitate this upgrade process. 
			For example to allow data to be 
		copied from the relational EMF store to a temporary XML Resource, create the new database and
		schema and then copy the information back.</p>
	</section>
  </body> 
</document>