<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
	Copyright 2005-2006, Elver.org (http://www.elver.org).

	Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
	you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
	You may obtain a copy of the License at

		http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
	distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
	WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
	See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
	limitations under the License.
-->

<!--
	@author <a href="mtaal@elver.org">Martin Taal</a>
	@version $Revision: 1.1 $ $Date: 2006/08/03 09:58:08 $
-->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
	"-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
	"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document> 
	<header> 
		<title>Elver History</title> 
	</header> 
	<body>
		<p>The Elver project originates from the company <a href="http://www.springsite.com/en">Springsite</a>. The 
			first focus of Springsite was to facilitate the developer and increase his/her 
		effectiveness when developing software.</p>
		
		<p>
		To achieve this a XML application framework was developed. The main feature 
		of this framework is its ability to model using xml schemas. Based on the xml schema model the framework
		generates java source code and data maintenance (web) views. These views automatically (with zero coding) 
		support complex xml schema structures such as multi-occurence choices with recursive types. 
		This makes it possible to define a model in XML Schema and have a working information management system without coding.
		Only the business functions had to be hand-coded to finish the solution. 
		</p>
		<p>
		Over time we noticed that it was, for a small company like ours, difficult to keep up with the 
		developments taking place in the open source space. In addition we wanted to re-develop our framework from
		scratch.
		</p>
		<p>
		We decided to organize and do this re-development in a different way and started the Elver project.
		Our aim with the Elver project is to achieve a broader use of our technology, have more contact
			with other developers and increase the quality of our work.
		</p>
		<p>Please continue reading <a href="goal.html">here</a>
		for the main goal of the Elver project.</p>
	</body>
</document>
