<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
	Copyright 2005-2006, Elver.org (http://www.elver.org).

	Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
	you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
	You may obtain a copy of the License at

		http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
	distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
	WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
	See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
	limitations under the License.
-->

<!--
	@author <a href="mtaal@elver.org">Martin Taal</a>
	@version $Revision: 1.1 $ $Date: 2006/08/03 09:58:08 $
-->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
	"-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
	"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document> 
	<header> 
		<title>Philosophy</title> 
	</header> 
	<body>
		<p>The Elver project aims to combine existing open source technologies to develop 
		a code and ui generation framework which takes away a lot of 
		standard work of the software developer. Within the Elver project we focus on modeling, code
		generation and ui generation using XML Schemas.
		</p>
		<section>
			<title>XML Schema</title>
		<p>Our experience with XML Schema over the past years have been very positive. We like the
		flexibility and power of the syntax. In addition we have noticed that it it is very efficient to
		define a model using XML Schemas (in contrast to using advanced and complex modeling tools). 
		</p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Code Generation</title>
		<p>It is our belief that code generation is the future for software development. Most, if not all, plumbing
		code can be replaced by a code generation framework. In addition code generation can take care of many
		business rules if supported by the modeling language. The <a href="http://www.eclipse.org/emf">EMF project</a>
		is an example of a code generation framework for XML Schemas.</p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>UI Generation</title>
		<p>Even more than with standard coding we think that developers time is 'wasted' on ui development. Especially
		standard data maintenance views take to much development time in relation to the actual value these functions
		have for the end-customer. By using a powerfull modeling language as XML Schema as the 
		input for a ui-generation framework we think that it is possible to generate advanced web-UI's with 
		very little coding.
		</p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Our approach</title>
		<p>We are committed to:</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Use and adhere to open standards</li>
			<li>Integrate and extend existing technologies to assemble a complete solution</li>
			<li>Develop open source solutions to facilitate a broad use of our and other's technology</li>
		</ul>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
