<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
	Copyright (c) 2005, 2006 Springsite BV (The Netherlands) and others
	All rights reserved. This program and the accompanying materials
	are made available under the terms of the Eclipse Public License v1.0
	which accompanies this distribution, and is available at
	http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html
-->

<!--
	@author <a href="mtaal@elver.org">Martin Taal</a>
	@version $Revision: 1.4 $ $Date: 2006/09/13 16:05:49 $
-->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
	"-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
	"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document> 
	<header> 
		<title>CVS</title> 
	</header> 
	<body>
		<p>The source code of the EMF - JPOX integration is stored in Eclipse.org cvs here:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>host: dev.eclipse.org</li>
		<li>repository: /cvsroot/technology</li>
		<li>module: org.eclipse.emft/teneo</li>
		</ul>
		<p>
			<strong>The source code in cvs is updated on a daily basis and contains experimental
				new features which can (temporarily) break already existing functionality and tests.
				There is no guarantee that the code in cvs will work in anyway.</strong></p>
		<section id="projects">
			<title>Projects in CVS</title>
		<p>The cvs repository has the following structure and projects:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>doc: contains this website</li>
		<li>examples: contains the samples and tutorial projects. Samples has all the model projects which are used as the basis for the test cases. The tutorial project contains the tutorials used on this website.</li>
		<li>plugins: this is the main folder. The following jpox related projects are present here:
			<ul><li>org.eclipse.emf.teneo: generic part of the runtime layer</li>
			<li>org.eclipse.emf.teneo.annotations: the jpa annotations</li>
			<li>org.eclipse.emf.teneo.eclipse: the generic part of the ui additions to eclipse for the Teneo right-click menus</li>
			<li>org.eclipse.emf.teneo.jpox: the main jpox project containing the mapping logic, jpox annotations and runtime layer</li>
			<li>org.eclipse.emf.teneo.jpox.eclipse: jpox specific part of the ui additions to eclipse</li>
			<li>org.eclipse.emf.teneo.libraries: common libraries (for example log4j).</li>
			</ul>
		</li>
		<li>tests: contains the test cases:
			<ul>
				<li>org.eclipse.emf.teneo.commontest: this project contains the test case part which is common for JPOX and Hibernate.</li>
				<li>org.eclipse.emf.teneo.jpox.libraries: jpox libraries, not distributed as part of the build, used during testing.</li>
				<li>org.eclipse.emf.teneo.jpox.test: jpox test cases (junit)</li>
			</ul>
		</li>
		</ul>
		<p>In addition there are several feature projects and build related projects.</p>
		<p><strong>Several of the above projects use third party libraries during the build process. The 
		plugin projects have dependencies defined on these libraries. However because of licensing these
		libraries are not publically accessible in Eclipse cvs. The third party libraries have to be 
		downloaded separately.</strong></p>
		<p>We use the standard Eclipse code format with the line length set to 120, the formatter profile
		can be downloaded <a href="../download/elver-code-profile.xml">here</a>.</p>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
