<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
	Copyright 2005-2006, Elver.org (http://www.elver.org).

	Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
	you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
	You may obtain a copy of the License at

		http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
	distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
	WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
	See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
	limitations under the License.
-->

<!--
	@author <a href="mtaal@elver.org">Martin Taal</a>
	@version $Revision: 1.2 $ $Date: 2006/08/24 21:27:43 $
-->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC
	"-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
	"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document> 
	<header> 
		<title></title> 
	</header> 
	<body>
		<section>
			<title>Introduction</title>
				<p>The Elver project focuses on combining code, persistency and UI generation solutions. 
					Elver Persistency implements persistency solutions 
					for generated Java objects by integrating code generation frameworks 
					and existing persistency technologies.</p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Elver Persistency moves to Eclipse.org as Teneo within EMFT</title>
			<p><strong>Elver persistency is in the process of moving to eclipse.org. Elver persistency will be continued as the Teneo project in the EMFT project.
			The current status:</strong></p>
			<ul>
			<li>The source code has been moved to Eclipse cvs. The new main java package name: org.eclipse.emf.teneo.</li>
			<li>Currently we are working on the build process.</li>
			<li>Support is given on both the 
			EMFT newsgroup as the Elver mailinglist. When the build process at eclipse.org is operational, support will move completely to the
			EMFT newsgroup.</li></ul>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>EMF Persistency</title>
				<p>Integrating EMF with existing persistency solutions, combines the power of a 
					code generation framework like EMF 
				and the power of storage, caching and querying of sophisticated object-relational mapping and persistency software.</p>
				<p>EMF has been integrated with two persistency solutions:</p>
				<p><strong><a href="hibernate/index.html">Hibernate:</a></strong> The EMF - Hibernate integration (alpha status) has just been released and supports
				persisting of basic EObjects, ELists with 1:n, n:m, one-way, two-way and contained relations. EMF Objects can be retrieved
			using HQL queries.</p>
				<p><strong><a href="jpox/index.html">JDO/JPOX:</a></strong> The EMF - JPOX integration (alpha status) supports
				all EMF and JDO 2.0/JPOX features. EMF objects can be persisted in most major relational databases and retrieved using an EMF resource approach or 
					advanced JDOQL queries.
				</p>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
